extracts.
supplied by a sub sub librarian.
It will be seen that this mere painstaking burer and grubworm of a poor
devil of a subsub appears to have gone through the long Vaticans and street
stalls of the earth, picking up whatever random allusions to whales he could
anyways find in any book whatsoever, sacred or profane. Therefore, you must
not in every case at least take the higgledy piggledy whale statements
however authentic in these extracts for veritable gospel slogy. Far from it as
touching the ancient authors generally as well as the poets here appearing.
These extracts are solely valuable or entertaining as affording a glancing
bird's eyee view of what has been promiscuously said, thought, fancied,
and sung of Leviathan by many nations and generations, including our own.
So far thee well, poor devil of a subsub, whose commentator I am. Thou
belongs to that hopeless salow tribe which no wine of this world will ever
warm, and for whom even pale sherry would be too rosy strong, but with whom
one sometimes loves to sit and feel poor devilish too, and grow convivial upon
tears, and say to them bluntly with full eyes and empty glasses, and in not
altogether unpleasant sadness, "Give it up, subs!" For by how much the more
pains you take to please the world, by so much more shall you forever go
thankless. Would that I could clear out Hampton Court and the tilleries for you.
But gulp down your tears and hile off to the royal mast with your hearts. For
your friends who have gone before are clearing out the sevenstoried heavens
and making refugees of long pampered Gabriel, Michael, and Raphael against
your coming. Here you strike but splintered hearts together. There you
shall strike unsplinterable glasses.
Extracts.
Quote, "And God created great whales."
Genesis.
Quote, "Leviathan maketh a path to shine after him. One would think the deep to be hy." Job.
Quote. Now the Lord had prepared a great fish to swallow up Jonah. Jonah.
Quote, "There go the ships. There is that Leviathan whom thouast made to play therein." Psalms.
Quote, "In that day the Lord with his swore and great and strong sword, shall
punish Leviathan, the piercing serpent, even Leviathan, that crooked serpent,
and he shall slay the dragon that is in the sea." Isaiah quote, "And what things soever besides
cometh within the chaos of this monster's mouth, be it beast, boat, or
stone, down it goes all incontinently that foul great swallow of his, and
perisheth in the bottomless gulf of his ponch." Holland's Plutarch's morals.
Quote, "The Indian sea breedth the most and biggest fishes that are among which
the whales and whirlpools called bellena take up as much in length as 4 acres or
arpens of land." Holland's ply quote scarcely had we proceeded two days
on the sea when about sunrise a great many whales and other monsters of the
sea appeared. Among the former, one was of a most monstrous size. This came
towards us open-mouthed, raising the waves on all sides and beating the sea
before him into a foam. Took Lucian, the true history.
Quote, he visited this country also with a view of catching horse whales, which
had bones of very great value for their teeth, of which he brought some to the
king. The best whales were catched in his own country, of which some were 48,
some 50 yards long. He said that he was one of six who had killed 60 in two
days.
Other orther's verbal narrative taken down from his mouth by King Alfred AD 890.
Quote, "And whereas all the other things, whether beast or vessel, that
enter into the dreadful gulf of this monster's whale's mouth, are immediately
lost and swallowed up, the sea gudgeon retires into it in great security, and
there sleeps." Montaigne, apology for Raymond Sabond.
Quote, "Let us fly. Let us fly. Old Nick, take me if it's not Leviathan,
described by the noble prophet Moses in the life of the patient Job Rables.
Quote, "This whale's liver was two cartloads stos annals.
Quote, the great Leviathan that maketh the seas to see like boiling pan."
Lord Bacon's version of the Psalms.
Quote, "Touching that monstrous bulk of the whale or orc, we have received
nothing certain. They grow exceeding fat in so much that an incredible quantity
of oil will be extracted out of one whale."
Ibid. History of life and death.
Quote, "The sovereign thing on earth is pariceti for an inward bruise." King Henry.
Quote, "Very like a whale, Hamlet.
quote which to secure no skill of leech's art moat him avail but to return
again to his wounds worker that with lowly dart denting his breast had bred
his restless pain like as the wounded whale to shore flies through the mine the fairy queens
whales the motion of whose vast bodies can in a peaceful calm trouble the ocean till it boil
Sir William Davinant, preface to Gondbert.
Quote, "What Spermaceti is, men might justly doubt, since the learned
Hosemanis, in his work of 30 years saith plainly, Nessio quid seat." Sir T. Brown
of Spermaceti and the Spermaceti whale vita his ve quote like Spencer's talis with his
modern flail he threatens ruin with his ponderous tail their fixed javelins in
his side he wears and on his back a grove of pikes appears
Waller's battle of the summer islands quote by art is created that great Leviathan
called a commonwealth or state in Latin.
Kitas, which is but an artificial man.
Opening sentence of Hobbes's Leviathan.
Quote, "Silly man soul swallowed it without chewing as if it had been a
sprat in the mouth of a whale.
Pilgrim's progress."
Quote, "That sea beast, Leviathan, which God of all his works created hugest that
swim the ocean stream. Paradise lost."
Quote, "There Leviathan, hugest of living creatures in the deep, stretched
like a promontory, sleeps or swims, and seems a moving land, and at his gills
draws in, and at his breath spouts out a sea." Ibid.
quote, "The mighty whales which swim in a sea of water and have a sea of oil
swimming in them." Fuller's profane and holy state.
Quote, "So close behind some promontory lie the huge leviathan to attend their
prey, and give no chance but swallow in the fry, which through their gaping jaws
mistake the way." Dryen's Annis Miraabulus.
Quote, "While the whale is floating at the stern of the ship, they cut off his
head and tow it with the boat as near the shore as it will come, but it will
be a ground in 12 or 13 ft water."
Thomas edges 10 voyages to Spitsburgen in purchase.
Quote, "In their way they saw many whales sporting in the ocean, and in
wantedness fuzzing up the water through their pipes and vents which nature has
placed on their shoulders."
Sir T Herbert's voyages into Asia and Africa. Harris Call.
Quote, "Here they saw such huge troops of whales that they were forced to
proceed with a great deal of caution for fear they should run their ship upon
them. Chin's sixth circumnavigation.
Quote, "We set sail from the Elba, went northeast in the ship called the Jonas
and the Whale. Some say the whale can't open his mouth, but that is a fable.
They frequently climb up the mass to see whether they can see a whale, for the
first discoverer has a ducket for his pains." I was told of a whale taken near
Shetland that had above a barrel of herrings in his belly. One of our
harpooners told me that he caught once a whale in Spitsburgen that was white all
over a voyage to Greenland AD 1671.
Harris call.
Quote, "Several whales have come in upon this coast." F ano652
180 ft in length of the whale bone kind came in which as I was informed besides
a vast quantity of oil did afford 500 weight of baine the jaws of it stand for
a gate in the garden of Pitferin Cibalds F and Kinros quote myself have agreed to try whether
I can master and kill this spermiceti whale for I could never hear of any of
that sort that was killed by any man such as his fierceness and swiftness.
Richard Strafer's letter from the Bermudas, Philosophical Transactions, AD 1668.
Quote, whales in the sea god's voice obey ne primer.
Quote, "We saw also abundance of large whales, there being more in those
southern seas, as I may say, by 100 to one, than we have had to the northward
of us."
Captain Cow's voyage round the globe, AD 1729.
Quote, "And the breath of a whale is frequently attended with such an
insupportable smell as to bring on a disorder of the brain."
Ulo's South America.
Quote, "To 50 chosen sils of special note, we trust the important charge, the
pedicote. Oft we have known that seven-fold fence to fail, though stuffed
with hoops and armed with ribs of whale.
Rape of the lock."
Quote, "If we compare land animals in respect to magnitude with those that
take up their abode in the deep, we shall find that they will appear
contemptable in the comparison. The whale is doubtless the largest animal in
creation." Goldsmith, natural history.
Quote, "If you should write a fable for little fishes, you would make them speak
like great whales." Goldsmith to Johnson.
Quote, "In the afternoon we saw what was supposed to be a rock, but it was found
to be a dead whale, which some Asiatics had killed and were then towing ashore.
They seem to endeavor to conceal themselves behind the whale in order to
avoid being seen by us." Cook's voyages.
Quote, "The larger whales, they seldom venture to attack. They stand in great
dread of some of them and that when out at sea they are afraid to mention even
their names and carry dung, limestone, juniperwood and some other articles of
the same nature in their boats in order to terrify and prevent their too near approach.
Uno vonil's letters on banks and salander's voyage to Iceland in 1772.
Quote, "The spermiceti whale found by the nantiquas is an active, fierce
animal and requires vast address and boldness in the fishermen." Thomas
Jefferson's whale memorial to the French minister in 1778.
Quote, "And pray, sir, what in the world is equal to it?" Edmund Burke's
reference in Parliament to the Nantucket whale fishery.
Quote, "Spain, a great whale stranded on the shores of Europe." Edmund Burke somewhere.
Quote, "A 10th branch of the king's ordinary revenue said to be grounded on
the consideration of his guarding and protecting the seas from pirates and
robbers is the right to royal fish, which are whales and sturgeon, and
these, when either thrown ashore or caught near the coast, are the property
of the king." Blackstone quote soon to the sport of death the
crews repair Rodmond unairring or his head suspends the barbed steel and every
turn attends. Falconer's shipwreck.
Quote, "Bright shown the roofs, the domes, the spires, and rockets blew
self-driven to hang their momentary fire around the vault of heaven. So fire with
water to compare the ocean serves on high, upspouted by a whale in air to
express unwieldy joy." Kalper on the Queen's visit to London.
quote, "10 or 15 gallons of blood are thrown out of the heart at a stroke with
immense velocity."
John Hunter's account of the dissection of a whale, a smallsized one.
Quote, "The aorta of a whale is larger in the boar than the main pipe of the
waterworks at London Bridge, and the water roaring in its passage through
that pipe is inferior in impetus and velocity to the blood gushing from the
whale's heart." Paleley's Theology.
Quote, "The whale is a mamiferous animal without hind feet." Baron Kouvier.
Quote, "In 40° south, we saw Spermaceti whales, but did not take any till the
1st of May, the sea being then covered with them.
Colin's voyage for the purpose of extending the spermicetti whale fishery."
Quote, "In the free element beneath me swam, floundered and dived in play, in
chase, in battle, fishes of every color, form, and kind, which language cannot
paint, and mariner had never seen. From dread leviathan to insect millions
peepling every wave, gathered in Scholes's immense like floating islands,
led by mysterious instincts through that waste and trackless region, though on
every side, assaulted by voracious enemies. Whales, sharks, and monsters
armed in front or jaw with sword, saws, spiral horns, or hooked fangs.
Montgomery's whirled before the flood.
Io pan Io sing to the finey people's king. Not a mightier whale than this in
the vast Atlantic is, not a fatter fish than he flounders round the polar sea.
Charles Lamb's Triumph of the Whale.
Quote, "In the year 1690, some persons were on a high hill observing the whales
spouting and sporting with each other when one observed, "There, pointing to
the sea, is a green pasture where our children's grandchildren will go for bread."
Oed Macy's history of Nantucket.
Quote, "I built a cottage for Susan and myself and made a gateway in the form of
a Gothic arch by setting up a whale's jawbones."
Hawthorne's twice told tales.
Quote, "She came to bespeak a monument for her first love who had been killed
by a whale in the Pacific Ocean no less than 40 years ago." Ibid.
Quote. "No, sir. It is a right whale," answered Tom. I saw his spout. He threw
up a pair of as pretty rainbows as a Christian would wish to look at. He's a
real oil butt, that fellow. Cooper's pilot.
Quote, "The papers were brought in, and we saw in the Berlin Gazette that Wales
had been introduced on the stage there."
Echerman's conversations with Gera.
Quote, "My God, Mr. Chase, what is the matter?" I answered. We have been stove by a whale.
Narrative of the shipwreck of the whale ship Essex of Nantucket, which was
attacked and finally destroyed by a large sperm whale in the Pacific Ocean.
By Owen Chase of Nantucket, first mate of said vessel, New York, 1821.
Quote, "A mariner sat in the shrouds one night. The wind was piping free. Now
bright, now dimmed, was the moonlight pale, and the phosphor gleamed in the
wake of the whale as it floundered in the sea.
Elizabeth Oaks Smith.
Quote, "The quantity of line withdrawn from the boats engaged in the capture of
this one whale amounted altogether to 10,440 yards, or nearly six English miles.
Sometimes the whale shakes its tremendous tail in the air, which
cracking like a whip, resounds to the distance of 3 or four miles. Scoresby,
quote, "Mad with the agonies he endures from these fresh attacks, the infuriated
sperm whale rolls over and over. He rears his enormous head, and with wide
expanded jaws, snaps at everything around him. He rushes at the boats with
his head. They are propelled before him with vast swiftness and sometimes
utterly destroyed. It is a matter of great astonishment that the
consideration of the habits of so interesting and in a commercial point of
view so important an animal as the sperm whale should have been so entirely
neglected. or should have excited so little curiosity among the numerous and
many of them competent observers that of late years must have possessed the most
abundant and most convenient opportunities of witnessing their habitudes.
Thomas Beiel's history of the sperm whale 1839.
Quote, "The Kashalo sperm whale is not only better armed than the true whale,
Greenland, or right whale in possessing a formidable weapon at either extremity
of its body, but also more frequently displays a disposition to employ these
weapons offensively, and in a manner at once so artful, bold, and mischievous as
to lead to its being regarded as the most dangerous to attack of all the
known species of the whale tribe."
Frederick Debel Bennett's Whailing Voyage Round the Globe, 1840.
Quote, October 13. There she blows sung out from the mast head. Where away,
demanded the captain. Three points off the lee bow, sir. Raise up your wheel.
Steady, steady, sir. Mast head. Ahoy. Do you see that whale now? I I sir, a shaw
of sperm whales. There she blows. There she breaches. Sing out. Sing out every
time. I I sir, there she blows. There, there, th there she blows. Bows, bows.
How far off? 2 miles and a half. Thunder and lightning so near. Call all hands.
J. Ross Brown's etchings of a whailing cruise. 1846.
Quote. The whale ship Globe on board of which vessel occurred the horrid
transactions we are about to relate belonged to the island of Nantucket.
Narrative of the globe by Lelay and Hussy survivors AD 1828.
Quote, "Being once pursued by a whale which he had wounded, he parried the
assault for some time with a lance, but the furious monster at length rushed on
the boat, himself and comrades only being preserved by leaping into the
water when they saw that onset was inevitable."
Missionary Journal of Tyman and Bennett.
Quote, Nantucket itself said, "Mr.
Webster is a very striking and peculiar portion of the national interest. There
is a population of 8 or 9 thousand persons living here in the sea, adding
largely every year to the national wealth by the boldest and most persevering industry.
Report of Daniel Webster's speech in the US Senate on the application for the
erection of a breakwater at Nantucket, 1828.
Quote, "The whale fell directly over him and probably killed him in a moment."
The whale and his capttors or the whaleman's adventures and the whales
biography gathered on the homeward cruise of the Commodore Priebal by Reverend Henry T. Chver.
Quote, "If you make the least damn bit of noise," replied Samuel, I will send you to hell.
Life of Samuel Commtock, the mutineer, by his brother, William Commtock,
another version of the whale ship globe narrative.
Quote, "The voyages of the Dutch and English to the northern ocean in order,
if possible, to discover a passage through it to India, though they failed
of their main object, laid open the haunts of the whale." McCullik's commercial dictionary.
Quote, "These things are reciprocal. The ball rebounds, only to bound forward
again, for now, in laying open the haunts of the whale, the whaleman seem
to have indirectly hit upon new clues to that same mystic northwest passage from
something unpublished.
Quote, "It is impossible to meet a whale ship on the ocean without being struck
by her near appearance. The vessel under short sail with lookouts at the mast
heads eagerly scanning the wide expanse around them has a totally different air
from those engaged in regular voyage currents and whailing USXX.
Quote, "Pedestrians in the vicinity of London and elsewhere may recollect
having seen large curved bones set upright in the earth, either to form
arches over gateways or entrances to aloves. Uh, and they may perhaps have
been told that these were the ribs of whales, tales of a whale voyager to the Arctic Ocean."
Quote, "It was not till the boats returned from the pursuit of these
whales that the whites saw their ship in bloody possession of the savages
enrolled among the crew."
Newspaper account of the taking and retaking of the whale ship Hobamac.
Quote, "It is generally well known that out of the crews of whailing vessels,
American, few ever return in the ships on board which they departed.
Crews in a whaleboat."
Quote, "Suddenly, a mighty mass emerged from the water and shot up
perpendicularly into the air. It was the whale."
Miriam Coffin or the whale fisherman.
Quote, "The whale is harpooned to be sure, but be think you how you would
manage a powerful unbroken colt with the mere appliance of a rope tied to the
root of his tail."
A chapter on whailing in ribs and trucks.
Quote, "On one occasion I saw two of these monsters, whales, probably male
and female, slowly swimming one after the other within less than a stones
throw of the shore. Tiarra del fuego over which the beach tree extended its
branches Darwin's voyage of a naturalist.
Quote stern all exclaimed the mate upon turning his head and saw the distended
jaws of the large sperm whale close to the head of the boat threatening it with
instant destruction. Stern all for your lives. Wharton the whale killer.
Quote, "So be cheery, my lads. Let your hearts never fail while the bold
harpaner is striking the whale.
Nantucket song.
Quote, "Oh, the rare old whale mids storm and gale in his ocean home will be
a giant in might where might is right and king of the boundless sea."
Whale song.